Preliminary Guide to the Horace Mann Hawthorne-Mann family correspondence, 1853-1865 and undated (bulk 1864-1865)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Horace Mann Hawthorne-Mann family correspondence 1853-1865 and undated, bulk 1864-1865
Mann, Horace, 1844-1868
0.2 linear feet Extent: 17 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
mannhorace
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Horace Mann Hawthorne-Mann family correspondence was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2000.
Biographical Note
Son of American educator, reformer, and U.S. Congressman, Horace Mann (1796-1859).
Collection Overview
Primarily letters to Mann from his family and the family of Nathaniel Hawthorne. Correspondents include Sophia Hawthorne, Rose Hawthorne, Una Hawthorne, brother George Mann, mother Mary Tyler Peabody Mann, and Elizabeth Peabody. Topics include family activities and travels, especially comments on Mann's descriptions of San Francisco and the Sandwich Islands [now the Hawaiian Islands]; Nathaniel Hawthorne's death and burial; Abraham Lincoln's death and burial; and opinions about Civil War events, battles, and personalities. Includes a letter from Elizabeth Peabody (undated) describing her two visits to President Lincoln and mentioning General Hitchcock's opinions about Lincoln and the Civil War. In addition, there is a carte-de-visite of Nathaniel Hawthorne. Acquired as part of the Alfred and Elizabeth Brand Collection of Rare Books and Manuscripts.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Mann, Horace, 1844-1868; Mann, Mary Tyler Peabody, 1806-1887; Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer, 1804-1894; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Hawthorne, Sophia Peabody, 1809-1871; Hawthorne, Una, 1844-1877; Lathrop, Rose Hawthorne, 1851-1926; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Death and burial; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Public opinion; Mann family; Hawthorne family; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Public opinion; Carte-de-visite; Alfred and Elizabeth Brand Collection of Rare Books and Manuscripts
Contents of Collection
- Accession 2000-0354
  - Letters To Horace Mann
    - From Rose Hawthorne, 1863 March-1864 October
      - 1863 March 3
        Letter written during Hawthorne's youth.
      - 1864 October 30
        An informal letter.
    - From Una Hawthorne, 1864 March-1864 August
      - 1864 March 3
        Topics include a military ball, the Sandwich Islands, and events in Concord.
      - 1864 April 28
        Topics include Julian Hawthorne and Mann's description of San Francisco.
      - 1864 May 30
        Topics include Julian Hawthorne, Una Hathorne's studies, and Mann's dangerous pursuits.
      - 1864 August 3
        Topics include a camping expedition to Mt. Monadnock, her father's (Nathaniel Hawthorne's) death, Mann's description of the Hawaiian Islands, a fair for colored children, and family and friends.
    - From George Mann, 1864 May-1865 April
      - 1864 May 29
        Topics include Nathaniel Hawthorne's funeral and his burial location in Sleepy Hollow.
      - 1865 April 18
        Topics include the death of Abraham Lincoln, church services, and the reaction to Lincoln's death in Boston.
    - From Mann's Mother, Mary Tyler Peabody Mann, 1864 May-1865 April
      - 1864 May 30
        Topics include Nathaniel Hawthorne's funeral.
      - 1864 July 23
        Topics include the Civil War, troop movements, battles, and specific military leaders such as Grant and Jackson.
      - 1865 April 20
        Topics include Lincoln's death and Reconstruction.
    - From Sophia Hawthorne, 1864 October 30
      Topics include the character of her husband, Nathaniel Hawthorne, and the difficulty of life after his death. The letter also contains a carte-de-visite of Nathaniel Hawthorne.
    - From Elizabeth Peabody, no date
      Topics include her visits with Lincoln and General Hitchcock's comments on the Civil War.
  - Letter to Elizabeth
    - From Sophia Hawthorne, 1858 November 21
      Topics include her family, travels to Europe, and a visit with the Brownings.
  - Letter to Mary Mann
    - From Rose Hawthorne, December 9 (no year)
      Topics include her health and her child's education.
  - Letter to [Nathaniel Peabody]
    - From Sophia Hawthorne, 1853 October 20
      Topics include the family's social engagments and activities in England.